Guide to the Ron Grunwald Papers, 1973 - 1980 UA.30.01.0041
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ron Grunwald papers
1973 - 1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Grunwald, Ron
UA.30.01.0041
0.5 Linear Feet
Ron Grunwald was an undergraduate at Duke University during the late 1970s. This collection contains materials reflecting his participation in student activism movements at Duke University and in the community, especially the Duke Southern Africa Coalition and the Radical Academic Union. Types of materials included are: printed matter, posters, newsletters, flyers, clippings, correspondence, memoranda, financial records, and an audiocassette. The bulk of material is from 1977 to 1980. Major subjects included are: student activism at Duke University, Associated Students of Duke University, international politics, human rights, Radical Academic Union, the Ku Klux Klan, Southern Africa Coalition, South Africa, unionization, Terry Sanford, and International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation. English.
500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Ron Grunwald Papers was received by the University Archives as a gift in 1995.
Historical Note
Ron Grunwald graduated from Duke University in 1980 (A.B., Trinity College). As an undergraduate student, he was a member of activist groups on campus including the Duke Southern Africa Coalition and the Radical Academic Union. The Southern Africa Coalition at Duke University concerned itself with human rights in South Africa as well as corporate divestment in the United States. The coalition sponsored the conference "Universities and Southern Africa" in 1978. The Radical Academic Union at Duke University protested President Terry Sanford's position on the board of International Telephone and Telegraph. Grunwald also corresponded with the Associated Students of Duke University and the American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees regarding unionization at Duke.
In the local community, he was associated with the North Carolina Public Interest Research Group, the Northeast Coalition for the Liberation of Southern Africa, Triangle Vigil Committee and the Kudzu Alliance/Citizens Against Shearon Harris Nuclear Power Plant. The Triangle Vigil Committee organized against Ku Klux Klan presence in North Carolina and planned vigils to alert the public to current Klan activities, especially the Greensboro, N.C. killings in 1979.
Ron Grunwald is currently a faculty member at Duke University.
Collection Overview
Contains printed matter, posters, newsletters, flyers, clippings, correspondence, memoranda, financial records, and an audiocassette concerning protest activities at Duke University and in the community.
Related Material
Terry Sanford. Papers, 1926-1995 and n.d.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Terry Sanford Records and Papers, 1945-1998.
University Archives, Duke University.
Eisinger, Jana, The Divestment Campaign at Duke University: Stepchild of the Civil Rights Movement.
University Archives, Duke University.
Student movements -- North Carolina; Clippings (information artifacts); Posters; Civil rights movements -- North Carolina; Sound recordings; Antinuclear movement -- North Carolina; Human Rights -- Africa; College students -- Political activity -- United States; Corporate divestiture -- South Africa; International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation; Grunwald, Ron; Grunwald, Ron; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- North Carolina; Sanford, Terry; AFSCME; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity
- Container List
  - American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) Campaign, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - East-West Expressway extension, ca. 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kudzu Alliance, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina Public Interest Research Group (NCPIRG), ca. 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Northeast Coalition for the Liberation of Southern Africa (NECLSA) Conference, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Radical Academic Union and International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation (ITT), 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Southern Africa Coalition
    - ca. 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ca. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ca. 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ca. 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Triangle Vigil Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Oversize
  Scope and Contents note
  Oversize materials are located in map cabinet drawer 8.
  - Handbooks
    - Irwin, Bob and Gordon Faison. ed. by David H. Albert "Why nonviolence? Nonviolence theory and strategy for the anti-nuclear movement," April 1978 (Box 1)
    - Radioactivist Handbook, a manual on: affinity groups, non- violence, civil disobedience, and the forthcoming Barnwell, S.C. anti-nuclear demonstration (September 29-October 1), 1979 (Box 1)
  - Posters (4)
    - An Evening of Diverse Entertainment a benefit for Southern Africa Coalition featuring Lisa Uyanik and the Mobile City Band, circa 1978 (Box 1)
    - South Africa Coalition, campus events, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Southern Africa Coalition, Conference on: Universities and Racism, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Southern Africa Coalition "Stop Banking on Racism!" circa 1977 (Box 1)